welcome to meditating with John Breaux
Vicki Lauri sorry about the slight delay
on our start this morning we had a minor
technical glitch which my techno god
amar solved very readily so as I
mentioned I'm John robic he I'm a
cognitive psychologist and a cognitive
scientist at the University of Toronto I
study phenomena like mindfulness
scientifically experimentally and I
study related phenomena like Insight
flow mystical experience the cultivation
of wisdom transformative experience
exception I've also been a practitioner
of the pasta meditation met a
contemplation in Tai Chi Chuan for 29
years
and I've taught those three
professionally for almost 20 years this
is a progressive course and if you're
joining us for the first time of course
welcome to stay but I recommend you go
back and look at the previous teaching
for teaching sessions so that's like day
one day three and Monday's previous one
will certainly believe the videos that
are teaching sessions and you could
catch up and it was one yesterday as
well you can catch up on the principles
that have been taught and then join us
as you wish we do meet every day at 9:30
a.m. every weekday we do not meet on
Saturdays and Sundays we meet every
weekday Mondays through Fridays and
there is a teaching session every Monday
so Monday is Dharma day I will teach you
a principle take you through an exercise
so you get a direct perfect spiritual
understanding and explain to you how you
can incorporate it into your practice
and build on the previous skills and
sensitivities that have helped you to
cultivate so today is not a teaching day
today is just a sitting day but even on
the sitting days after we sitting I'll
do a quick review of where we're at and
and there are even on the sitting days
and as well there will be a period at
the end for Q&A s so it's a personal to
meet in the sits we have good research
that have you sense that you're meeting
with other people you will keep up a
practice
where it's much more difficult to do
this on your own and also there will be
the review and probably most importantly
while you're learning there will be the
Cuban ace so attending the Sitz is also
a very good idea and one other thing and
I'm very pleased to see this in the blue
tradition we talked about the Buddha the
Dharma and the Sangha assigned as a
community and a community is starting to
form and a community is very very
helpful for getting people into a
transformative way of life please set
your phones to do not disturb so you can
give your full attention to this
practice I'll now do a quick review the
first lesson was about finding your
Center but the back side to side with
your torso in your head if you Center
really savoring it that centering your
attention by stepping back and looking
at your mind labeling your distractions
with an ING word returning your
attention to your breath centering your
attitude neither fighting nor feeding
that distracted monkey mind the second
last the second lesson teaching session
was on rooting the appropriate form of
relaxation not a relaxation that takes
you into sleep but that takes you into
mindfulness and we had you know three
lines front center and back where we did
the process of looking listening
loosening letting it flow letting it go
finding your route then we learned how
to find our flow in meditation you know
we did that in the abdomen expanding
both the cross and in interceptive
awareness noticing different kinds of
sensations putting a real challenge on
our attention really deeply integrating
introspection and interception together
we did that here the heart area the
shoulders the back and then one flow so
that we have a peripheral awareness
we're following the whole of the breath
through the whole of the torso or focal
awareness isn't rdn where we're without
force to get without force and yet
trying to do baby breathing and we have
a focal awareness here at a field
awareness throughout our bodies
yesterday we learned about the proper
right concentration that it's in the
Eightfold Path
that there's right concentration which
means there is wrong concentration we're
trying to break and it will take time
while trying to break the habit of the
concentration we have Leonard which is
people yelling at us pulling our mind in
from the outside sticking it onto
something instead we pursued the idea of
the correct form of concentration is a
constant noticing a constant renewing of
interest by trying to be you know not
just being present but being present at
differing present - but be present in
and through and with our stimulus
constantly opening it up with soft
vigilance the term that Ellen Langer
introduced we do that of course by after
we begin meditation we count our breaths
not because we're entering into any
judgment what we're doing is we count
our breaths so that when we are
distracted we take a quick moment and
note that's what it was like to have
that continuity that momentum of
mindfulness that entering the stream all
right so that's the review so please
remember always in that order to find
your Center find your route find your
flow find your focus don't
hyperventilate don't force your
breathing like you have to sometimes
make minor adjustments if you feel like
you've lost your Center like if you're
having a more pressing distraction try
initially like maybe two three or four
times it's just label and return to the
breath it gets to be too compulsive
though right remember the principle
we're performing ourselves we do not
want to be merely enduring okay with
this is an educational situation not an
imprisonment situation so if like if you
got a pain and you've tried it four
times to label it return to the bus and
it's just getting overwhelming then do
what you need to do to alleviate it and
that return to your breath all right I
think that's everything so that we can
get started it's wonderful to be with
all of you here today so it's a
beautiful sunny day in Toronto which is
a nice uplift given the situation we're
all in alright everyone let's prepare to
sit we will begin when I say begin
begin
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice buying as best you can to
integrate looking cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition so we'll
take some questions now the first is
from Nikolas I'm a curette who asks
questions pretty much every day it's
good to hear from you Nikolas and the
question of the day is you liked your
striped shirt t-shirt say uh-huh
I guess I haven't really thought about
it that much
I also go through a phase where I'll be
reading I'll be wearing reading I'll be
wearing solid colored shirts I'm trying
to for obvious reasons of social
distancing I'm sort of trying to go
through all of my wardrobe right now to
reduce the laundry I live in an
apartment and so the laundry is communal
so I have to stretch things out to try
and reduce social distancing so that's
why you'll see maybe proud a variety of
shirts that I normally presented Rainier
lovely easier meditation technique and
methodology you and Gillian lores which
you've developed over years of practice
and study or have you I needed
influenced by other teachers I'm
teaching both I was taught as I said by
what was called the Taichi and
meditation Center and I was taught by
three different teachers the the past
now the meta and the Tai Chi Chuan over
an extended period I also have done some
online stuff I've read a tremendous
amount on these areas but I also as I've
mentioned and this is a huge influence I
do a lot of cognitive scientific and
cognitive psychological investigation
and and bringing that to bear so it's a
combination both of like what I've been
taught the three things it's a
combination of what I've been taught by
teachers
what I've learned through scientific
investigation and my own practice so
there's sort of three three sources
coming together and I hope a way that's
accessible and available to others flynn
of raw Optus discipline of raw asks this
is my third day taking part and I've
noticed that I caught myself growing
impatient and I opened my eyes before
the 15 minute mark is this normal
yes yes very much your brain wants to
get you into you so we have a tremendous
familiarity by Tobias complaint also
always is trying to get you into a very
familiar state we talked about this
before the notion of encoding
specificity your brain does not only
store fact it stores the context in
which facts are stored and it fuses
those together and it really like their
context familiar ways of being situated
in your mind your body because of course
that's that's a high survival value it's
familiar it's highly predictive etc and
so your brain will try like when you're
trying to get in between falling asleep
which is familiar to you and moving
around which is familiar to you and even
daydreaming which is familiar to you is
trying to you don't get between all of
those it's a very novel and unfamiliar
place then your monkey mind doesn't like
it your brain doesn't like it and so yes
there'll be quite a bit of like Oh to
try and get you out truck I know what
that's like and it's very familiar to
people don't beat yourself up about it
when you come out try to notice what's
going on
be mindful of it and then try to go
right back in if you can't and then next
time you get the impulse see if you can
label that for maybe four or five
breaths before you have to do it into it
and again like always slowly try to
erode away the resistance until you
afford change this is from Rohit
yonis do you know whether THC CBD
enhances the meditative practice or not
no I do not I suspect it might not
because I what I know about this is it
tends to have a tunneling effect on on
attention which may seem like it's
improving your focus but generally what
it's doing is it's actually reducing the
capacity to open up in a disciplined
manner and it tends to perhaps conduced
towards being a little bit more a
motivational which might be a challenge
for continuing on in this practice and
thirdly I strongly recommend trying not
to do that much additional change to
your psychophysiology because of
encoding specificity if you're inducing
a particular in a psychophysiological
state with pharmacological intervention
the problem there is your brain is going
to get it's been a fuse and it's going
to fuse that state with the mindfulness
practice what MIT which will make it
hard for you to transfer it to your life
in general
Christelle rebuilt this is my second day
and I can't help but laugh after nine to
10 breaths is this normal
yes that's another instance of what I
described yesterday so if you know
Christelle yesterday maybe you're here
yesterday that's another example of that
parasympathetic rebound phenomena
don't worry about your sanity or
anything like that just label it return
to the breath lay it just just allow it
to be part of how you're practicing how
are you practicing hi mark mark
lefebvre's back any tips for coming out
of meditation seems like something
helpful if there are some standard
strategies to help integrate it into our
lives I will definitely be teaching you
later there's specific class a sort on
integration of what you can do right now
try to remember what I said about trying
to open your eyes and continue that
state of mind and body now try this try
to set up a marker for yourself perhaps
whenever you put your hand in your
pocket or whenever you go through a
doorway and what those markers are is
they're like a little call to meditation
and when
you do that when you encounter like I'm
going through the doorway you stop and
you do a quick neck don't do the whole
thing because it'll take a long time
just as close as you can
a quick centering and routing a sense of
coming into your the flow of your body
of mind and do you like maybe a one or
two breaths the possum I do that
throughout the day and then when you do
that rather than coming and see you can
carry it forward as you're walking
around but like I say later we'll come
back to a specific set of practices you
can do for cultivating into integral
integrity where integrity doesn't just
mean sort of a moral thing it means more
specifically the practice of integrating
what you're cultivating in your practice
with your everyday life here at Kroger
yesterday I asked about crime thank you
for the language of the struggle between
the sympathetic and parasympathetic I've
been practicing for the year and never
had that language thank you you're
welcome
Kiera I'm glad that's helpful this is an
example I'm not trying to be overly
self-promotional but it's an example of
how understanding the cognitive science
could be of great benefit in the
teaching right and the learning of
mindfulness practices my question is if
I notice that struggle to to is strong
and I'm having trouble coaxing the puppy
back to the breath do you have any
suggestions for dealing with that one of
the things we're going to talk about in
so on Monday we're going to learn meta
contemplation and then the day I the
next lesson will start what's called
they'll be to might want to do is write
if that struggle is getting too much
then maybe you know reroute tap into the
fact that you've started to build up
some skilled momentum for the rooting
and the eccentric recenter even if
you're not off-centered recenter reroute
reflow again and count your breath again
before simply just trying to maintain
your Vipassana so do that for now but as
I said I wish I could teach you all
everything else once but unfortunately
we're human beings we have to learn
through time but we will have specific
things that I will teach you about how
to deal with both distractions hindrance
and hindrances things that cause you to
resist
yep your practice Andre affair as well
as getting led away from focusing on my
breath my my market and I realize that
labeling and returning I've also know
that I tend to zone out and almost
forget that I'm meditating is that I
can't
is that okay should I label zoning out
forgetting yes label that and catching
yourself from zoning out that's it
that's a really that's sort of you know
that's the trippy monkeymod instead of
chattering that's distraction it sort of
lows you into right zoning out and
losing that continuity of contact with
your breath
definitely label that come back you
might want to reengage flow because it
might be also that your brain is trying
to take you towards sleep okay this is
from McCready any tips on keeping your
breath natural when I'm focusing on
their breath I tend to force my
breathing and what I noticed I've
returned to natural breathing I start to
force it again yeah so this is a
difficulty some people face so so what
are the things that recommend this for
other reasons but one of the things
that's very helpful for this is to get
into a moving mindfulness practice where
you Center your attention where your
breath will be regulated right with the
practice but the focus of your attention
for examples on movement I strongly
recommend and there's online courses you
take up some cheek on or some Tai Chi
because those moving mindfulness
practices help to break up that sort of
self-fulfilling prophecy of anxiety
around the breath and then when she get
that moving mindfulness and you can sort
of focus on your body in a different way
and your your breathing is natural you
can build up a different association
between mindfulness and breath in the
body so if this is a pervasive issue for
you you need to consider taking that out
Nick Kennedy
hi Nick good to see you again should our
counting be resting at a count of ten or
continuent until we are away from it
when should we go back to only following
their breath yeah accounted
10 is a good idea I think that's good if
you feel that you get it if I can't tell
you this but when you get that sense
that you're getting that momentum of
mindfulness that it starts becoming a
self-organizing process rather than a
process you're forcing into place it
won't ever it with the wheel a long time
before that's completely the case but if
you got a sense that at least some of
your attention is now self-organizing
rather than forced then that's you've
counted for long enough so sorry I
rushed through some of those questions
that are not trying to be insensitive I
was trying to do today is trying to
answer as many questions as I can
because I won't see you guys again until
Monday thank you for joining it's always
appreciated as I said building the
assignment together is really important
as always I want to thank amar and Jason
for their help please subscribe to the
video channel to be notified of the next
video also on my channel you'll find a
lot of relevant material for how to
situate this practice into a more
broadly reaching ecology of practices
how you can you know maybe confront some
of broader issues facing us with a more
resilient than adaptive framing and so
this is all there to try and provide
help and afford people's transformation
and resilient responsiveness we'll do it
as I said we're doing this every weekday
morning at 9:30 EST and I'll see you all
on Monday for our next Dharma session
and where the way we'll learn about meta
contemplation thank you very much for
your time